Eleanor Medill Patterson Papers
Eleanor Medill Patterson Papers
1924-1936
Patterson, Eleanor Medill, 1881-1948
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American newspaper editor, publisher of the Washington (D.C.) Times-Herald. Correspondence, incoming and outgoing; manuscripts; and published material by and/or about Arthur Brisbane and William Randolph Hearst.
149447
Biographical History
Eleanor Medill Patterson was born on November 7, 1884 in Chicago, Illinois and died in July, 1948 at "Dower House", the seventeenth century Maryland manor house that once housed the Earls of Calvert and Baltimore. She was the granddaughter of Joseph Medill, founder of the Chicago Tribune, daughter of Robert Wilson Patterson, editor of the Chicago Tribune and sister of Joseph Medill Patterson, editor and publisher of the New York Daily News. Miss Patterson was educated in Boston at Miss Hersey's School. Her first husband was Count Joseph Gizycka and her second husband was Elmer Schlesinger. At the time of her death she was editor, publisher and sole owner of the Washington, (D.C.) Times-Herald. She is survived by her daughter Felicia Gizycka and granddaughter Ellen Cameron Pearson Arnold, child of columnist Drew Pearson.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The papers of Eleanor Medill Patterson include Correspondence, Subject files, Manuscripts and Published material. It also includes correspondence of Arthur Brisbane and William Randolph Hearst.
Correspondence includes incoming and outgoing correspondence. The incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author, the outgoing correspondence is arranged chronologically. Subject file includes notes and promotion material arranged alphabetically by subject. Manuscripts, includes manuscripts of speeches and notes and a speech of another person, arranged alphabetically by type. Published material, includes a newspaper clipping.
Arthur Brisbane includes incoming correspondence arranged alphabetically by author and outgoing correspondence arranged chronologically. It includes published material arranged by type and two short manuscripts of statements. William Randolph Hearst includes incoming correspondence arranged alphabetically by author and outgoing correspondence arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Publishing, printing and book arts; Journalism; Brisbane, Arthur, 1864-1936; Hearst, William Randolph, 1863-1951; Patterson, Eleanor Medill, 1881-1948 Archives; Newspaper editors, United States; Newspaper publishing, United States; Publishers and publishing, United States; Women journalists, United States; Women publishers, United States; Correspondence.; Editors.; Journalists.; Publishers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - Brisbane, Arthur
      See also Arthur Brisbane
      - 1924, 1927-1930 (Box 1)
      - 1931 (Box 1)
      - 1932 (Box 1)
      - 1933 (Box 1)
      - 1934 (Box 1)
      - 1935, 1936, undated (Box 1)
    - Farley, James A. (Box 1)
    - H - W, unidentifiable (Box 1)
    - Hearst, William Randolph, 1930-1935; undated (Box 1)
      See also William Randolph Hearst
  - Outgoing
    - 1930-1936, undated (Box 1)
- Subject file
  - Notes (Box 1)
  - Promotion (Box 1)
  - Photograph (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Notes, re Washington (D.C.) newspaper competition (Box 1)
  - Speech (Box 1)
  - Of others - speech (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Newspaper clipping about (Box 1)
- Arthur Brisbane
  - Incoming correspondence, C - W, unidentifiable (Box 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1932-1935, undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts (Box 1)
  - Published material
    - Articles about (Box 1)
    - Articles by (Box 1)
- William Randolph Hearst
  - Incoming correspondence, B- (Box 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence, 1931-1933; 1935,; undated (Box 1)
  - Subject file
    - Menus (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts (Box 1)
  - Published material about (Box 1)